<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-11-14T22:09:52+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">observing the unobservable without visualization</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/observing-the-unobservable/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="observing the unobservable without visualization"/><published>2023-11-29T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/observing-the-unobservable</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/observing-the-unobservable/"><![CDATA[<p>Bohr’s atomic model was developed in 1913, and was a natural progression from his contemporary Rutherford’s model of the atom as an entity with a dense nucleus and electrons in orbit around it. Importantly, Bohr’s model accounted for the discrete spectral lines found in hydrogen whereas Rutherford’s model could not. Bohr postulated that an atom consists of orbiting electrons which can instantaneously “jump” to different quantized, discrete energy levels. Rutherford held that these quantum electron jumps were too difficult to visualize. This begs the question: are scientific theories required to be visualizable? While a theory that uses only entities and behaviors that are visualizable makes it more easily communicable, it does not need to be a strict requirement because scientific theories that are not visualizable can still provide powerful predictions and explain underlying causal structures, which I hold to be inherently valuable in themselves.</p> <p>The trouble with defining a scientific theory has to do with the fact that these theories must be both scientific and useful. However, these terms are not black and white, and can sometimes conflict or overlap with one another. I take scientific to generally mean something derived from applications of the scientific method — by most definitions, the scientific method requires the following three steps: abduction (the process by which scientists create a hypothesis that is the best explanation of phenomena), deduction (inferring what should be the case if the hypotheses are the case), and induction (testing the hypothesis). I take useful here to mean pragmatically useful; a theory that can be applied to inform predictions or explain phenomena which can then be used to undertake more scientific inquiry. It does not make much sense for a theory to be labeled scientific, however, if it is not also useful. Because Bohr developed his theory through applications of the scientific method, I hold that the concern here has to do with its usefulness. That is, in order to determine whether a scientific theory must necessarily be visualizable, we must ask whether the usefulness of a theory is inextricably tied to its visualizability.</p> <p>If we can show that a theory that was not visualizable at the time of its conception was later found to be useful, we have shown that visualizability is not a necessary condition for usefulness. Bohr’s atomic model was useful according to my definition: it accurately predicted spectral lines in hydrogen, it directly led to explanations of electron behavior such as Bohr’s quantization rule, and laid the foundation for other scientists to explore frameworks of quantum theory such as matrix mechanics and led to such discoveries as Heisenberg’s uncertainty principle. Bohr’s atomic model, though not visualizable, played a part in developing an entirely new direction of physics and directly led to new scientific discoveries and thus can be said to be useful.</p> <p>Further, it is not useful to immediately dismiss a scientific theory simply because it is hard to visualize right now — we may be able to visualize it in the future through better technology, for example. The theory might also be difficult to depict under the current scientific paradigm, but this lack of visualizability might also provide a reason to break out of the paradigm in the form of a Kuhnian anomaly and subsequent paradigm shift. These anomalies are extremely useful because they incite revolutions and new schools of thought which may be able to better explain phenomena in the future. If we dismiss a theory simply because we cannot visualize it, we lose the potential for a paradigm shift.</p> <p>A potential cause for concern might be the counterargument that unvisualizable scientific theories are simply not pragmatic because of a difficulty to communicate them. While this incommunicability is a valid concern, and theories that are more able to be explained to laypeople or those unfamiliar with a specific field will likely hold more explanatory power, the theory will still be useful for the most part. That is, scientists in the field will still be able to use the theory, and have the potential to create more widely understandable explanations from the groundwork that the initial theory has laid.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="bohr,"/><category term="atoms,"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For theories about the unobservable underlying causal structures of the world (like Bohr’s theory of the atom), should we require that the theory use only entities and behaviors that are visualizable?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">circular arguments in 19th and 20th century science</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/circularity-19th-century-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="circular arguments in 19th and 20th century science"/><published>2023-11-13T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-13T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/circularity-19th-century-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/circularity-19th-century-science/"><![CDATA[<p>Physicists in the late 19th and early 20th centuries made the following assumptions about electrically charged particles which were thought to make up all physical objects: The particles would oscillate in simple harmonic motion when e-m radiation was absorbed. The particles would emit e-m radiation while oscillating.</p> <p>At the time, it was impossible to provide evidence for the existence of these charged oscillators, but we now know that these oscillators exist in the form of electrons which oscillate around an atom’s nucleus in quantized energy levels. However, earlier physicists made these assumptions regardless and justified their use of the assumptions through various means, including the following two arguments. The first argument is the following: Maxwell’s laws, which can explain all electric and magnetic phenomena, entail that the only cause of e-m waves is accelerated charges. It has been shown that the electric and magnetic fields radiated from furnace walls were changing at regular frequencies, and thus would only be produced by electrical charges that were oscillating at the frequencies of the waves they produced. The second argument, now, goes as follows: Planck used the assumption that the walls of the furnace are made up of electrically charged oscillators to predict a distribution of frequencies. This calculated distribution was consistent with the true distribution of frequencies emitted from the walls, and thus the assumption is confirmed by its accurate prediction. I argue that the second justification is stronger than the first, due to the first’s circular nature, and further, I note that the two arguments can be combined in order to produce an argument stronger than both of them individually.</p> <p>In order to show that the first argument is circular, let us break the argument up into its premises and conclusions:</p> <p>P1: Maxwell’s laws suggest that the only cause of electromagnetic waves is accelerated changes in electric and magnetic fields.</p> <p>P2: The electromagnetic radiation emitted from the walls of furnaces exhibits characteristics consistent with electromagnetic waves. C: Therefore, the walls of the furnaces are composed of electrically charged oscillators because these oscillators would be a natural source of the regularly changing electric and magnetic fields required to produce such radiation. The implicit connection between premise 1 and the conclusion is where the circularity becomes apparent: the conclusion attempts to prove that furnace walls must be made of electrically charged oscillators because changes in electric and magnetic fields are required to produce electromagnetic waves – the latter half of the previous statement is an exact copy of premise 1. In other words, the conclusion essentially restates the assumption from premise 1, rather than providing independent justification for the idea that electrically charged oscillators must be a natural source of these fields. The second argument is essentially the hypothetico-deductive method: Planck assumed the hypothesis of the existence of electrically charged oscillators in order to make his predictions about frequencies emitted by the wall, and deduced that his prediction aligned with the true results of these frequencies when measured. This argument has the usual pitfalls of using the hypothetico-deductive method in this way: it is limited by the amount of predictions and confirmations made, and that there may have been various other assumptions that Planck could have made that provided coherent deductions (perhaps similar to the assumptions made in our current understanding of quantum mechanics). However, because of the inherent circularity in the first argument, it is more compelling. However, we can use the previous two arguments to create a third, stronger argument that aligns more with the scientific method. I hold that scientific arguments which appeal to the scientific method as I define it are stronger than the simple predictive argument that the hypothetico-deductive argument makes. By most definitions, the scientific method requires the following three steps: abduction (the process by which scientists create a hypothesis that is the best explanation of phenomena), deduction (inferring what should be the case if the hypotheses are the case), and induction (testing the hypothesis). We can use the first argument I detailed above during the abductive process — we can conclude that a reasonable hypothesis (rather than a conclusive scientific statement) would be that “the walls of the furnaces are composed of electrically charged oscillators” because “these oscillators would be a natural source of the regularly changing electric and magnetic fields required to produce such radiation.” Then, we can use the predictions made by Planck in the second argument to deduce the measurements that would need to be true in order for the hypothesis to be the case. Finally, we can test the hypothesis during the inductive process, and thus we have scientific grounds to make the assumptions about these oscillating particles. A counter argument would be that the first argument is actually stronger on the grounds that a more charitable reading would include the following implied premise: P3: Electrically charged oscillators are the only possible source of regularly changing electric and magnetic fields. While this does seem to eliminate some circularity, there is still no justification or basis for P3, and the conclusion also seems to restate P3 almost directly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="electricity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Does the 19th and 20th century physicist argument in favor of assuming the walls of the furnaces are at least 'partially composed of electrically charged oscillators' hold any weight?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">leibniz’s impossible request</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/leibniz-impossible-request/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="leibniz’s impossible request"/><published>2023-09-29T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-29T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/leibniz-impossible-request</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/leibniz-impossible-request/"><![CDATA[<p>After Newton published his Principia Mathematica, which outlined the cause of planetary motion (namely, gravity), one of Newton’s peers Gottfried Leibniz revealed a major criticism. Leibniz held that while Newton had provided a good description of the properties of gravity and its connection to planetary movement, he had not given a causal explanation for why gravity exists and why it behaves the way it does. To this, Newton responded that there is no need to provide a causal explanation of gravity because this cause cannot be deduced from the current phenomena observed. I hold that Newton was completely valid in his rejection of Leibniz’s criticism because forcing scientists to follow a (potentially) endless line of questioning hurts science: continuing to fixate on these questions might hinder scientific progress that can happen with the universal laws we have now. Further, science thrives on testable hypotheses because these tests provide an empirical foundation for theories that can be built off of these claims, and Newton would have been unable to provide a truly testable causal explanation for the phenomena observed.</p> <p>Imagine that Newton had given an answer to the cause of gravity, and call this Cause A. Newton did not know what Cause A was, but thanks to Einstein, we do: the cause is embedded in Einstein’s theory of general relativity. However, we can also ask what the cause of general relativity is, and we can call this Cause B. This is a recursive process — we can always ask “why?” and it is extremely unclear where we should stop (Cause C? Cause D? What about Cause Z?). René Descartes believed that the “first cause” (also known as the “prime mover”) had its roots in God. This implies that we would need to keep searching for causes and can finally stop after finding the cause that was set into motion by God. However, to most contemporary philosophers, this is an arbitrary stopping point — even those who believe in God can always ask “why did God set this cause in motion above all others?” or even “why does God exist?” Because these stopping points are arbitrary, we are left with a chain of questioning known as an infinite regress that leaves us with endless speculation without a single falsifiable answer. We can have no scientific progress if we must answer every question about the causes of phenomena before applying or accepting the theories that describe them.</p> <p>Also, an extremely important aspect of science is its focus on testable hypotheses, because these tests serve as an empirical foundation in order for more theories to be developed. At the time of Newton’s publication of Principia, there was not much information on the limitations of his theory of gravitation that we know today, such as the perihelion precession of Mercury’s orbit (where Mercury’s point closest to the Sun shifts over time) and gravitational lensing (the way light bends due to gravity). Newton and his contemporaries simply did not have the technology to observe any of these phenomena. However, our advanced satellite cameras, telescopes, space expeditions, and advances in precise measuring devices have helped us confirm the theory of general relativity. Limited by the technology available at the time, any kind of hypothesis that Newton could make would not be grounded in any kind of empirical evidence. Thus, we could not apply these hypotheses to the real world, and a major aspect of scientific progress can be defined as applying theories to the real world and seeing what new discoveries we can make about nature. The question of asking “what is the cause of gravity?” is a valid scientific question: science is also clearly concerned with causality (We can see this through Newton himself, who sought to discover the cause of planetary motion). However, it is not valid to assume that gravitation as a theory is invalid because Newton did not explain why gravity exists. This is because it becomes a hindrance to science when we hyperfixate on untestable scenarios (such as the theory of relativity when we did not have the proper resources to test it), taking time, resources, and energy away from the scenarios that can actually be tested. The field of science was greatly impacted and furthered by Newton’s theory of gravitation: for example, Newton’s laws were used to calculate the specific trajectory of the Voyager spacecrafts which went on to take detailed pictures of Jupiter and Saturn, which helped improve our scientific understanding of the formation of these planets. This might not have happened when it did if Newton himself had believed that his theory must be grounded in a cause before he chose to publicize it.</p> <p>One potential counter argument to my claim may be that we can conceive of a reality in which Newton could, in fact, have come up with a causal explanation that would have been testable. For example, we can imagine that Newton had provided an explanation following Descartes’ theory that planetary movement and the gravity we feel on Earth is due to particles called corpuscles that move in vortices with no gaps between them, and which produce the centripetal motion we observe in planetary orbits. This may have been closer to a causal explanation than the one Newton provided, because it employs a mechanism of physical particles interacting with each other, which is more tangible than the theory of gravitation. This could have been tested by measuring the force acting on a ball as it falls to the ground, and comparing this with a model of all possible accelerations and forces of corpuscles acting on an imaginary ball. If the net acceleration in all directions experienced by the ball in the real world was equal to that of the imaginary ball, the theory would have been validated. While this is true, and we could conceive of a reality in which Newton proposed a testable theory, this is an extremely low bar for scientific testability and for causal explanations: Newton believed specifically that a causal explanation for a phenomena would have to be “derived from the phenomena,” meaning it required an explanation grounded in empirical evidence. However, the previous counterargument still would not fit his criteria for a causal explanation, because Newton did not have the technology necessary to test it, and would not have been able to come up with a rigorous way to collect the empirical data.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="newton,"/><category term="leibniz"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Should Newton have simply rejected Leibniz’s complaint that he hadn’t explained the causes of the properties of gravity?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the non-primitive nature of ‘primitive’ science</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/babylonian-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the non-primitive nature of ‘primitive’ science"/><published>2023-09-23T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-23T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/babylonian-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/babylonian-science/"><![CDATA[<p>Ancient astronomers sought to predict and retrodict the movement of the celestial bodies. Among these ancient astronomers were the Babylonians, who utilized empirical data to discover patterns about the way these bodies moved. They created what the Greeks called ephemerides: tables of data about the locations of celestial bodies. Here, the Babylonians were looking for patterns in large datasets to predict future events, just as we do now to conduct other kinds of scientific inquiry. However, these efforts by ancient astronomers are sometimes seen as primitive and unscientific. I claim that these statements qualifying Babylonian astronomy as unscientific are incorrect.</p> <p>In order to prove that Babylonian astronomy is, in fact, real science, we need to provide a clear definition of what “science” and the “scientific method” truly are. While philosophers have not collectively agreed on a solution to the demarcation problem, I define science here as any kind of study that employs the scientific method. As for the scientific method, I turn to Charles S. Peirce, who defines the process as having three key steps: “abduction (making conjectures or creating hypotheses), deduction (inferring what should be the case if the hypotheses are the case), and induction (the testing of hypotheses).” I go on to show that the Babylonians went through these three steps, thus they were doing successful science.</p> <p>Abduction is the first step in carrying out the scientific method and is the process by which scientists create a hypothesis that they will later test. Peirce’s definition of abduction includes the fact that the hypothesis must also be the best explanation of the phenomena, given current observations. Ancient Babylonian astronomers went through the process of abduction by forming the hypothesis that the position of celestial bodies can be predicted through patterns drawn from recording the positions of these bodies for many years. This was also the best explanation of the phenomena: Babylonians had known for many years that certain stars rose and set in the sky at known intervals — these stars were called ziqpu. The fact that ziqpu exist would be enough evidence for a logical inference that celestial bodies can be predicted through similar patterns.</p> <p>Babylonians also employed deduction. It follows that if the hypothesis (that patterns in celestial movement can be found by examining large datasets of this movement) is true, then it should be the case that we should be able to observe the location of a celestial body based on this pattern. For example, if the constellation Canis Major has been observed for the last fifty years in the wintertime, according to our hypothesis, we can deduce that the pattern is that Canis Major appears every year in the winter. Further, we can deduce that if we look up at the night sky in the winter, we will see Canis Major. This is why Babylonians wrote out their predictions for eclipses, the length of night and day, and length of seasons in so-called omen texts: they deduced that patterns found in their datasets meant that these previously observed natural occurrences would really happen again in the future.</p> <p>For our final stage in the scientific process, we must show that Babylonians practiced induction. That is, we need to show that they tested their hypotheses. We know this to be the case because of the Babylonian goal year texts. These texts contained predictions for the locations of celestial bodies and timelines of celestial events in the near future. Astronomers cross-referenced these goal year texts with their actual observations in order to refine their patterns.</p> <p>We have shown here that Babylonians did practice “real science” because they followed the scientific method. A contrarian might respond that adhering to the scientific method does not necessarily make a pursuit scientific. However, I doubt that anyone will disagree that one criterion for scientific discovery today is developing algorithms to predict future events. This is exactly what the Babylonians did — they derived patterns from big datasets in order to predict celestial events. So, even by this metric, ancient Babylonians were practicing science. Another possible rebuttal could be that the Babylonians only had primitive tools, so they could only do primitive science. However, I choose to answer this without any rigorous philosophical proof: Would we accept it if, in the distant future, humans deemed current science “primitive” due to what they believed to be underdeveloped tools? Likely not — we consider our current scientific endeavors to be truly scientific regardless of what tools may exist in the future.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="kuhn,"/><category term="peirce"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If one criterion for successful scientific inquiry used today is developing algorithms for predicting future events, then weren’t the Babylonians doing successful science by our own criteria?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the usefulness of ‘purely mathematical’ structures</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/purely-mathematical-structures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the usefulness of ‘purely mathematical’ structures"/><published>2023-09-17T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-17T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/purely-mathematical-structures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/purely-mathematical-structures/"><![CDATA[<p>Aristotle believed that true science provides us with explanations of the causes of the phenomena it studies. For example, true science (as it relates to astronomy) should seek to explain the cause of celestial bodies’ movement through physical models, rather than just provide mathematical models. The Jewish philosopher Maimonides echoed Aristotle’s view: he claimed that while Ptolemy’s model of the cosmos could accurately predict and retrodict the trajectory of celestial bodies, it does not “tell us in which ways the spheres truly are.” In other words, both philosophers thought that Ptolemy’s model of the cosmos was not true science, and thus should not be a goal of scientific inquiry. However, I argue that purely mathematical models that serve to accurately predict future events should be a goal of scientific inquiry.</p> <p>One condition for something to be a ‘goal of scientific inquiry’ is that it serves to further other scientific progress. This may sound cyclical, but let us remedy that by defining “true scientific progress” in Aristotle’s terms: progress towards something which explains the cause of certain phenomena. So, if we can show that there are examples of accurate purely mathematical or geometric models that inspire other “truly scientific” endeavors, we have shown that the model should be a goal of scientific inquiry. I will present two such examples: one hypothetical example which implements Ptolemy’s model, and one example involving Newton’s Law of Gravitation.</p> <p>For our first example, let us assume that we still do not know the cause of celestial motion, and further, that we only have Ptolemy’s mathematical model to inform us of the locations of the planets in our solar system. Let us also imagine that we are trying to land a craft on Mars in order to learn more about the composition of Martian soil. Under Aristotle’s definition of science, learning about the composition of Mars is true science — if we can discover what substances Martian soil is composed of, we can gain insight into how the planet was formed, what elements were necessary for its creation, and general information that explains the cause of various related phenomena. In order to land on Mars, we clearly also need an optimal landing spot on Mars and a trajectory that our spacecraft will take, avoiding celestial bodies along the way. To deduce this information, we also clearly need predictions of the positions of these celestial bodies and their trajectories during the time that our spacecraft is on its mission, and all of this information can be found through the ephemerides that Ptolemy created based on his mathematical model. Through this hypothetical example, we can see how Ptolemy’s mathematical model can contribute to the understanding of the causes of planetary phenomena. Since this model can serve to further science, it should be a goal of scientific inquiry.</p> <p>For our second example, let us turn to Newton’s laws — specifically, Newton’s Law of Universal Gravitation. The law states that “every particle attracts every other particle in the universe with a force that is proportional to the product of their masses and inversely proportional to the square of the distance between their centers.” Newton’s discovery is an extremely accurate prediction of everyday phenomena, including the motion of celestial bodies and how masses act as they fall. However, Newton’s law was not applicable in some extreme cases, like regions of high gravitation near black holes. In these regions, there exist phenomena that cannot be explained by Newton’s law: event horizons (a line past which even light cannot escape) and gravitational lensing (the bending of light due to an area of high gravitation). After observing these phenomena, Albert Einstein proposed his theory of General Relativity, which scientists now agree to be the best universal explanation of gravity. However, despite the issues in his causal understanding of gravitation, Newton’s mathematical model helped perform calculations to launch spacecrafts and satellites that sought to explain various phenomena. For example, Newton’s laws were used to calculate the specific trajectory of the Voyager spacecrafts. These spacecrafts then went on to take detailed pictures of Jupiter and Saturn, which helped improve our scientific understanding of the formation of these planets. Clearly Newton’s law helped further science and thus, these mathematical models should be a goal of scientific inquiry.</p> <p>Critics might argue that the pursuit of mathematical models might hinder the pursuit of an external truth. That is, they would rather spend their time focusing on the root cause of phenomena. However, in both examples above, the application of these mathematical models gave us more insight into the physical nature of the universe: both Ptolemy’s model and Newton’s law of gravitation helped us understand more about the composition of celestial bodies, and the nature of their creation. Another counterargument is that a focus on mathematical models can lead to an over-importance being placed on mathematical beauty. This leads to other, less aesthetic models not garnering enough scientific attention. For example, take the idea of supersymmetry. This is a theoretical phenomenon where each particle has its own symmetric partner particle. This idea is extremely mathematically elegant, but we haven’t seen any experimental evidence for this. Regardless, physicists spend time searching for evidence for this model rather than looking at less elegant models that may be supported by empirical evidence. This means we need to place restrictions on how we use mathematical models to conduct further scientific inquiry. We must understand that they are just models that we can use to predict and retrodict, rather than assuming that they provide a complete, causal explanation.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="kuhn,"/><category term="peirce,"/><category term="pragmatism"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Should the creation of purely mathematical structures that don’t claim to be accurate models of the physical world (like Ptolemy’s model) but which nonetheless serve as effective calculating instruments for predicting future events be a goal of scientific inquiry?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">aquitting darwinism of the accusation of intrinsic immorality</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/darwinism-and-morality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="aquitting darwinism of the accusation of intrinsic immorality"/><published>2023-09-01T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-01T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/darwinism-and-morality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/darwinism-and-morality/"><![CDATA[<p>Daniel Dennett, like Thomas Kuhn, notes that science is necessarily based in some kind of philosophy, and that the choices scientists make while “doing science” are framed by their perspectives and morals. That is, science is value-laden. Dennett deeply praises Charles Darwin’s theory of natural selection, but issues arise when we note that Darwin directly appeals to one of Thomas Malthus’ core ideas: “population explosion and famine were inevitable, given the excess fertility of human beings, unless drastic measures were taken.” Historical Malthusians have used this framing to argue for mass genocide and eugenics in order to “check” the human population. Dennett seems to off-handedly dismiss criticism of Darwin’s appeals to Malthus, and instead calls this appeal “purely logical.” The relevant critiques that may render Darwinism immoral for this use of Malthus would be the historical Malthusianism and social Darwinism that seem to logically follow. However, I argue that, while it is true that science is value-laden, Darwin’s theory is not intrinsically immoral in this sense because eugenicists and social Darwinists incorrectly project Darwin’s objective view on fitness onto their subjective racist and classist views and thus misrepresent Darwin’s theory as well as commit the naturalistic fallacy, so social Darwinism does not logically follow from Darwinism. A correct use would not ever justify eugenics, and thus the theory is not intrinsically immoral due to Darwin’s use of Malthus.</p> <p>In order to prove that social Darwinism does not logically follow from Darwinism, we must provide an account of what social Darwinism is. This is difficult because social Darwinists provide many, oftentimes conflicting, definitions. However, generally, social Darwinism is thought to be the idea of “survival of the fittest” (which was coined by social Darwinist Herbert Spencer, rather than Darwin himself) as it applies to human populations, rather than plants and animals as was intended by Darwin. This implies that those who are “more fit” will naturally rise to the top of society, while those who are weak and disadvantaged will naturally fall behind. Social Darwinism also became a justification for (and synonymous for) eugenics (to increase the amount of so-called-“fitter” humans in a population), laissez-faire capitalism (to strip poorer individuals of resources because only those who are “fit” ought to survive), and mass genocide (of those who were “less fit”).</p> <p>Social Darwinism hinges on the idea of a “survival of the fittest,” but social Darwinists seem to completely misunderstand what Darwin actually meant by the term “fitness.” Social Darwinists like Spencer take “fitness” to mean “physical fitness” according to their personal beliefs — they often see rich and White as equivalent with “fit,” while “poor and non-White” seem to mean “unfit.” However, Darwin’s fitness was simply a measure of reproductive success — a “fitter” organism is one that can produce more offspring, and a “fitter” trait is one that can help an organism survive in an environment. It is strange and anti-Darwinist, then, that many social Darwinists believe that poor individuals are the least fit, when poor people tend to have more children. Also, it is possible that we may be living in a starkly different social and economic system in just hundreds of years of time (which is clearly not enough time for evolution to occur) — why must we be best adapted to success in our current society, when it has the potential to change relatively quickly? Darwin never meant to apply the situation of organisms in nature to humans living in modern society for the reason my previous statements are problematic to social Darwinism: a struggle for existence to live in nature is fundamentally different from the struggle to live in modern society, thus Darwin’s theories are completely inapplicable to human society. Social Darwinists project their subjective racist, classist, and ethnocentric views on Darwin’s objective classification of fitness. This projection is a fundamental misunderstanding of Darwinism, and thus is not a valid interpretation. This framework is explicitly immoral, but does not logically follow from Darwinism, and thus does not render Darwinism itself immoral.</p> <p>Social Darwinism also hinges on the naturalistic fallacy, which is a fallacy of the form: “Something is the case in nature, thus it ought to be how humans operate.” It is clear to see how this is a fallacy through the example “it is the case that many animals are cannibals, then humans ought to be cannibals as well.” In the case of social Darwinism, Darwinism describes the world (this is how nature operates, through natural selection), it doesn’t prescribe our affairs (this ought to be how we operate, we must engage in a forced natural selection through eugenics, laissez-faire, and genocide). Further, Darwin is explicit in that natural selection has no agenda and no specific predetermined destination, unlike the eugenics that stems from social Darwinism.</p> <p>Another obvious issue of social Darwinism is that it is explicitly Lamarckian. Social Darwinists believe that social characteristics acquired during an individual’s lifetime (such as an ability to accumulate wealth under capitalism) can be passed down, which is why some social Darwinists sought to weed out people who they believed were not industrious enough, in order to “better” the gene pool. However, Darwin believed that there were certain heritable traits, and thus a correct usage of Darwinism would not justify this interpretation because these traits are not heritable.</p> <p>A clear counter argument presents itself: if Darwinists and social Darwinists derive their conclusions from the same three premises, accepting Darwinism due to these premises might accidentally validate social Darwinism, which we have already declared is immoral. However, an issue with this argument is that social Darwinists misapply one of these premises to human society — namely, Darwin’s premise that a struggle for existence is necessary for natural selection. The premise can be applied to the natural world because organisms in the wild have no way to mitigate against the dangers of predation, limited resources, environmental changes, and other natural factors. However, it cannot be applied to human society because human structures are immensely more complex: we have found ways to mitigate against all of the aforementioned dangers, and have developed structures to allow for the well-being of individuals, regardless of their “fitness.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="darwin,"/><category term="malthus"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Can we come up with an interpretation of Darwin’s use of Malthus which preserves our understanding of Darwin as true, but saves the theory from being intrinsically immoral?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">physical phenomena as ‘law of nature’</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/what-is-a-law-of-nature/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="physical phenomena as ‘law of nature’"/><published>2023-08-29T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-29T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/what-is-a-law-of-nature</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/what-is-a-law-of-nature/"><![CDATA[<p>19th century technology was able to show that Kepler’s laws were only an approximation for planetary movement. In reality, gravitational forces associated with all of the different celestial bodies (not just the un, as idealized by Kepler) led to the planets following a slightly different (though still elliptical) path than Kepler predicted. These actual observed trajectories are much more complex than can be explained solely through Kepler’s laws. On top of this, Kepler’s laws do not explain the causal nature of the movement of celestial bodies — they only provide an empirical framework to accurately predict and analyze their approximate motions. However, these kinds of “universal” laws are still important to scientific knowledge because they give us a framework to analyze the causes behind natural phenomena.</p> <p>To begin talking about universal laws and their importance, we need to define what a universal law really is, since it is not clear how (if a universal law is not an exact representation of what occurs in nature) they can be referred to as “universal.” I define a universal law to be a general mathematical formula or statement that can accurately describe patterns in nature. Universal laws also necessarily attempt to explain a truth about nature. However, universal laws also make assumptions about other factors being static, because it is impossible to account for every possible variable that affects the phenomenon. The “universality” comes from the law being applicable to all scenarios within the given scope.</p> <p>In order to see how universal laws provide us a framework to develop the causes of natural phenomena, I will show how two of Kepler’s laws led directly to the derivations of causal explanations for planetary movement. Kepler’s first law states that planets trace an elliptical path around the Sun: the ellipse is defined by placing the Sun at the first focus, and reflecting the Sun about the vertical axis as the second focus. This discovery was a shock to scientists at the time, who were fascinated with elegant mathematical symmetries. The assumption that all natural movement was symmetric and stable implied that celestial orbits acted in uniform circular motion at a constant speed. However, Kepler’s discovery directly opposed this belief, and allowed scientists to move towards providing more rigorous, empirical evidence for the causes behind natural phenomena. Kepler’s second law states that bodies move faster as they get closer to the Sun, and slower when they are farther out. This law similarly served to push scientists away from providing a divine explanation for their scientific reasoning, since the planets did not move at a constant velocity throughout their orbits. Further, it gave Newton, whose Law of Gravitation dealt with the causes of planetary motion, a reason to account for this change in speed and thus Kepler’s laws directly contributed to the discovery of a cause for this motion. In order to formally derive this cause, Newton had to develop his three laws of motion which fundamentally altered the way we think about all objects and their forces and movement, and revolutionized the (extremely scientifically important) field of classical mechanics.</p> <p>Nancy Cartwright provides a convincing argument as to why universal scientific laws may be problematic in her How the Laws of Physics Lie. She explains that scientific laws contain a lot of idealizations, which implies that we should not treat them as direct representations of nature or natural processes. When a universal law gives us an idealized result, we often forget that the real world will likely give us a different answer. If we take these universal laws as the natural truth, we may not explore why the real world is different from the idealized version that the model gives us, and thus may not ever delve into the causes behind the disparities, and these causes may actually be extremely scientifically useful. For example, Newton’s law of gravitation is idealized to be in a vacuum, and in a vacuum, both a feather and a bowling ball will fall at the same rate. However, due to air resistance these items will not fall at the same time in the real world. If we only look at the universal model, this may cause issues: we may not research the scientific discoveries associated with air resistance, such as fluid dynamics and the importance of considering all forces that apply to an object, which are both extremely scientifically important understandings. I agree with this argument, which is why we need to make a conscious effort to treat these universal laws as approximations that may not always be perfectly accurate. We need to explore the situations where the universal law and the real world give us different results, and make tweaks to the law as needed.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="kuhn"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If none of the physical phenomena that are claimed to 'follow a law of nature' actually conform precisely to that law then what exactly are we referring to as a 'law of nature'? Is it reasonable to consider laws that only approximately describe the behavior of the phenomena said to obey them to be important parts of scientific knowledge?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">darwin &amp;amp; the hypothetico-deductive method</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/darwin-hypothetico-deductive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="darwin &amp;amp; the hypothetico-deductive method"/><published>2023-08-26T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-26T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/darwin-hypothetico-deductive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/darwin-hypothetico-deductive/"><![CDATA[<p>Charles Darwin published his Origin of Species knowing that it was unreasonable to demand demonstrative proof of his theory of natural selection because it acted over such long periods of time. Scientists who opposed Darwin expected from him absolute proof and absolute certainty of his theory. Perhaps they wanted a direct observation of species evolving over an observable time frame, a fossil record with no gaps that showed every stage of species transition, or some kind of experimental demonstration of natural selection occurring. Historian Peter J. Bowler holds that no philosopher of science would accept this critique because we now view science as fallible. This fallibilist view of science implies a kind of tentativeness inherent in science, and emphasizes that scientific knowledge can be revised as new evidence is brought to light. This is in contrast with infallibilism, which suggests that science can provide us with theories that guarantee a certainty about the world. I argue that Charles Darwin used what we now call the hypothetico-deductive method to test his theory. Further, any challenge which aims to undermine the scientific nature of Darwin’s theory based on his usage of this method or utilizes the infallibilist position that this method is unscientific because it cannot guarantee truth is invalid.</p> <p>First we must discuss what the hypothetico-deductive method is and what it entails. The method is a way to systematically approach scientific inquiry, which involves forming a hypothesis, deducing predictions or retrodictions from the hypothesis (usually in the form of if…then…), conducting experiments or observations to test these predictions, and applying inductive reasoning to evaluate whether the outcomes of the experiments or observations align with the hypothesis. This method offers a potential solution to the problem of induction as popularized by philosopher David Hume, who argued that induction does not allow us to come to general claims based on specific observations. A famous example used by Karl Popper is the following: say we have only seen white swans in our lifetime. Employing induction, which aims to create a general theory given particular observations, we may believe that all swans are thus white. However, the existence of a black swan immediately falsifies our hypothesis. The significance is that no amount of evidence can ever guarantee a theory to be true, because all it takes to falsify it is a single counterexample. Scientists who opposed Darwin who emphasized a need for direct evidence that they thought guaranteed scientific truth may have been implicitly leaning towards an inductive process, such as an accumulation of evidence about species evolving. Popper places an extreme emphasis on falsifiability as a solution to the demarcation problem (distinguishing real science from non-science) and the induction problem: a scientific theory must be able to be proven wrong. The hypothetico-deductive method emphasizes deduction by encouraging scientists to make predictions and retrodictions, and emphasizes falsifiability by encouraging them to conduct experiments and observations to test whether their deductions were correct. However, it is important to note that this method does not guarantee scientific truth either: testing that a hypothesis cannot be falsified through various means does lend credibility to the theory, more so than just evidence for the theory through an inductive process would, but it does not guarantee truth.</p> <p>Now we can show specifically that Darwin was using this method by going through each step of the hypothetico-deductive method sequentially and showing that Darwin took each step:</p> <ol> <li> <p>Forming a hypothesis: Darwin hypothesized that species went through transformations through the process of natural selection.</p> </li> <li> <p>Deducing predictions or retroductions: Darwin predicted that if populations of species became isolated in different environments, natural selection would affect them differently and thus the species would look different after many generations.</p> </li> <li> <p>Conducting experiments or observations: Experimentation is very difficult with respect to evolution because the time for species to evolve with noticeable changes takes many generations and many years. So, Darwin mainly conducted thorough observations. For example, he traveled to the Galapagos islands to observe different populations of finches which had been isolated from each other on different islands. He noted that each island had different environments and saw that finches on each island had variations, particularly in the shape of their beaks.</p> </li> <li> <p>Applying inductive reasoning: He noted four subgroups of finches, each suited to their environment. Ground finches had short and thick beaks which allowed them to crack the hard nuts found in their corresponding island, cactus finches had long, pointed beaks which helped them feed from cactus flowers, tree finches had medium sized beaks which allowed them to eat insects and fruits, and warbler finches had thin beaks which helped them feed on insects. He compared these variations to the environments the finches lived in, and induced that they aligned with his theory.</p> </li> </ol> <p>Now that we have shown that Darwin was, in fact, using the hypothetico-deductive method, we must show that a challenge to Darwin’s theory that aims to undermine the scientific nature of this method is invalid. In order to do this, we must show that the method itself is scientific. I hold that a method is scientific if it aligns with the scientific method as outlined by philosopher Charles S. Peirce, which I find to be an exemplary explanation of how we ought to pursue scientific inquiry. Peirce defines the process as having three key steps: abduction (the process by which scientists create a hypothesis that they will later test), deduction (inferring what should be the case if the hypotheses are the case), and induction (testing the hypothesis). We can now show that the hypothetico-deductive method aligns with the scientific method by going through these three steps:</p> <ol> <li> <p>Abduction: This is trivial, as the first step of the hypothetico-deductive process is coming up with a hypothesis that is the best explanation of phenomena involved.</p> </li> <li> <p>Deduction: This is also quite trivial. The second step of the hypothetico-deductive method is deducing predictions or retrodictions in the form of if…then… statements.</p> </li> <li> <p>Induction: The final two steps of the hypothetico-deductive method are conducting experiments or observations and applying inductive reasoning to evaluate the hypothesis. These serve as the test of validity of the hypothesis meant by Peirce’s final stage of the scientific method.</p> </li> </ol> <p>So, we can see how the hypothetico-deductive method completely aligns with the scientific method, and thus is scientific. We must also show that a challenge to Darwin’s theory based on his use of the hypothetico-deductive method to test it because that method of testing cannot guarantee the truth of the hypothesis is also invalid. To prove this, I turn to my earlier discussion about the induction problem and Popper’s criterion of falsifiability. There is no scientific process that can yield absolute truth: the inductive process cannot because we always run the risk of finding a counterexample, and the hypothetico-deductive process cannot for the same reason. The difference though is that the latter process has a dedicated stage (experimentation and observation) to find the evidence that might falsify the theory. The more chances we give a theory to be falsified, the more sure we can be of its truth when it passes these tests. This critique is not reasonable because we can never guarantee truth by any method — at least the hypothetico-deductive method lends us more credibility by allowing the theory to withstand so many chances at falsifiability.</p> <p>We can imagine a counter argument which takes issue with the idea that Darwin is using the hypothetico-deductive method even though he is in a situation where he cannot necessarily check his predictions. For example, Darwin deduced that, if his hypothesis were correct, we would find intermediate species in the fossil record which showed transitional stages. However, he never actually found something like the wooly mammoth fossil, which looks similar to modern Asian elephants, and thus could have been evidence to support his hypothesis. This is true, and a valid counter argument — it would have been stronger for Darwin’s argument if he had found this evidence. However, Darwin did as much as he could at the time. I hold that scientific knowledge is provisional; that it is the best we can do at the current moment. Darwin was limited by his lack of knowledge about genetics, incomplete fossil record, and lack of technology, and had to make do with what observation he could conduct at the time — it was still scientific.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="darwin"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Would a challenge to Darwin’s theory based on his use of the hypothetico-deductive method to test it have been a reasonable critique?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">galton’s ‘law’ of variation vs. kepler’s law of planetary motion</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/galton-vs-kepler/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="galton’s ‘law’ of variation vs. kepler’s law of planetary motion"/><published>2023-08-26T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-26T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/galton-vs-kepler</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/galton-vs-kepler/"><![CDATA[<p>Through the careful and systematic observation of the celestial bodies recorded by Tycho Brahe, mathematician Johannes Kepler derived three laws that served as a “universal” description of planetary movement. A similar generalized law from another discipline, genetics, was proposed by Francis Galton, who discovered that variation of traits within a population of a species generally follows a normal distribution. I argue that Kepler’s laws can be said to be a universal “law of nature,” while the same cannot be said about Galton’s law. I also hold, however, that both laws are valuable to us as tools which can help in determining the underlying causal structures for the phenomena described by those laws.</p> <p>First we must define what a universal law really is, since it is not clear how if a universal law is not an exact representation of what occurs in nature, they can be referred to as “universal.” I define a universal law to be a general mathematical formula or statement that necessarily attempts to explain a truth about nature. Universal laws make assumptions about other factors being static because it is impossible to account for every possible variable that affects the phenomenon. The “universality” comes from the law being applicable to all scenarios within the given constraints. So, in order to deem a law as universal, we must first define the constraints under which the law is said to hold, then show that the law actually holds under these conditions. However, the conditions we define must allow for the pragmatic use of the law — it should not be so specific that the law has very little general use.</p> <p>Kepler’s laws are idealized to hold under the condition that the Sun is the primary body affecting the motion of the planets. This scope is clearly not too specific, because it allows us to use Kepler’s laws to come to conclusions about all bodies in our solar system. Even with this limited scope, the law can be used in many practical applications such as charting the course a spacecraft should follow, depending on the positions of certain celestial bodies. Kepler’s laws are also extremely accurate under this scope: they were able to retrodict all of the observations made by Tycho Brahe, and predict current observations within the solar system. So, by our definition, we can say that Kepler’s laws can be said to be a universal law of nature.</p> <p>In order to identify the scope we are meant to apply Galton’s law, we must remember that he developed his law of variation through his own biometric observations of traits within humans, sweet pea plants, dogs, and other organisms. It seems as though the law was meant to apply to all populations of all species, with an unclear scope. However, we now know that many trait distributions do not follow a normal distribution. For example, the mollusk Anomalocardia flexuosa, has been shown to have a normal distribution in the rainy season, a bimodal distribution in the early dry season, and a right-skewed distribution in the late dry season. Also, the distribution of leaf length in the Impatiens pallida has been observed to be distinctively skewed right in both crowded and uncrowded leaf distributions. These are not outliers — there are many cases in which populations do not follow a normal distribution of traits, perhaps due to the environment inhibiting their growth, polygenic traits (meaning some traits influence the expression of other traits), and predator-prey relationships. Because Galton has no way to clearly define these constraints, the law cannot be said to be “universal.”</p> <p>However, I have stated that both laws are valuable as tools for determining causal explanations of natural phenomena. Kepler’s laws described the natural phenomena of planetary motion. While Kepler did not provide a causal explanation for this phenomena, this work was done by Newton who used Kepler’s laws as a mathematical framework to theorize that a force called gravity pulled bodies towards each other at a force proportional to the square of their distances. So, the predictions and retrodictions that can be derived through Kepler’s laws allowed Newton to determine a causal explanation in the form of gravity.</p> <p>Similarly, Galton’s law describes the natural phenomena of the normal distribution of traits within a population. Again, while Galton did not provide a causal explanation for this distribution, we can develop theories using his law such as the existence of additive polygenic traits, random variation, and environmental factors on traits. The Central Limit Theorem (CLT) in statistics states that the distribution of the sum of a large number of independent and identically distributed random variables becomes approximately normal. In our case, the normal distribution can be explained if there are independent influences on traits by polygenic traits and the environment, and an additive effect of these polygenic traits, which we can categorize as random variables. So, the existence of traits that affect each other and are affected by the environment can provide a causal explanation for the observed normal distributions. So, both Galton’s and Kepler’s laws can help determine underlying causal explanations of natural phenomena.</p> <p>A potential counter argument might take issue with my definition of a universal law — it might state that a law does not need to have clearly defined constraints in order to be deemed a universal law. I believe that a law cannot be called universal when we are somewhat unsure of where it can be applied, but the more important part of my argument is that Galton’s law is still useful regardless of whether it is a universal law or not. I see less reason to argue the semantics of when to use the term “universal law” —- we should instead focus on the practical application of these laws, and recognize when they can be useful to science.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="galton,"/><category term="kepler"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is Galton's law of distribution of variations of traits in organisms a 'law of nature'?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a response on darwin’s behalf</title><link href="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/leibniz-and-darwin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a response on darwin’s behalf"/><published>2023-08-18T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-18T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/leibniz-and-darwin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://aditinnara.github.io/blog/2023/leibniz-and-darwin/"><![CDATA[<p>Just like the paradigm shift that resulted from Isaac Newton’s development of the law of universal gravitation, there was a similar paradigm shift in the field of biology that stemmed from Charles Darwin’s radical theory of evolution. Pre-Darwin, biologists believed that all organisms present on Earth were created by an omniscient “creator” or God. In the earth 19th century, Lamarck developed his theory of transmutation which stated that organisms were not fixed but rather changed over time to better suit the needs of the environment. This challenged the idea of a fixity of species created by an omniscient being — why would a God create animals that were not perfect, and thus needed to change over time. Darwin noticed that animals seemed well-adapted to their surroundings and that offspring seemed to resemble their parents, and theorized that, over time, the most useful traits were passed down through a process he called natural selection. A real critique of Newton’s theory by his contemporary Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz was that Newton did not provide a causal explanation for his theory of planetary movement. Similarly, we can imagine a Leibnizian critique of Darwin’s theory: “Without telling us the underlying causal mechanisms for both variation and inheritance, your theory of evolution is at best incomplete and is certainly not a full-fledged scientific theory.” To Leibniz, a causal mechanism was missing. However, I will argue that while Darwin and Newton’s theories are analogous in that both are missing causal explanations for their theories, the kind of critique I have mentioned is invalid for both Darwin and Newton and thus, their theories can be called “scientific.”</p> <p>First, we must discuss what both Newton and Darwin “give us” in their theories and what they do not. This will help us understand what kind of “causal mechanism” Leibniz and similar critiques are looking for. In Newton’s Principia Mathematica, he sought to explain the reasons planets move the way they do, as approximated by Kepler’s Laws. He theorized that a force called gravity pulled bodies towards each other at a force proportional to the square of their distances. However, Newton did not give us any explanation for why gravity exists, and how such a force could have come to be. Similarly, in Darwin’s Origin of Species, Darwin sought to explain the reasons that animals seemed well-adapted to their environments and why children resemble their parents. So, he theorized that organisms evolve through the mechanism of natural selection with the help of variations within a population. However, Darwin does not give an explanation for why variation exists or a biological mechanism for how inheritance works. We can see how these discoveries are analogous: neither of them provided explanations for the mechanism they describe, but they both do provide us with mechanisms that explain certain phenomena. Newton did not provide a causal mechanism of gravity but provided a mechanism for planetary movement. Darwin did not provide a causal mechanism for inheritance or natural selection, but did explain why offspring resemble their parents and why animals seem well-adapted to their environment. In the case of Newton, a causal mechanism would be similar to our current understanding of Einstein’s theory of relativity, which explains how the bending of spacetime creates the effect that gravity produces. Darwin’s theory of evolution could have been supported by the causal explanation that genes are passed down through DNA and gametes. I argue that any causal explanation Darwin or Newton could have provided would not have been scientific.</p> <p>I hold that a scientific theory must be testable for it to be called scientific. While this is in no way an exhaustive definition, if we can show that the causal mechanism would not have cohered with this criterion, we have proved that the theory would not have been scientific. I also hold that, for a theory to be testable, it must be both practically and pragmatically testable. Practically testable theories are those that can be physically tested with the equipment available to the tester at the time. For example, Einstein’s theory of relativity would not have been practically testable in Newton’s time because he did not have access to advanced space telescopes which would have revealed phenomena like gravitational lensing. Pragmatically testable theories are those that can be tested with available technology, but are too radical in the context of existing scientific beliefs. That is, the theory goes against the existing paradigm in such a way that the scientific framework to test the theory is completely lacking.</p> <p>Any causal explanation that Newton provided for his theory of gravitation would have likely been practically untestable. The prevailing idea at the time for the cause of planetary movement was the existence of tiny particles that “pushed” bodies (like planets) around. In order to test something like this, Newton would have needed advanced experimental devices, such as our advanced satellite cameras, telescopes, space expeditions, and advances in precise microscopes, which just were not available in his time. Limited by the technology available at the time, any kind of hypothesis that Newton could make would not be grounded in any kind of empirical evidence, and thus, can be labeled as unscientific.</p> <p>Similarly, any causal explanation for natural selection would have likely been pragmatically untestable. We need to take into account the “scientific stock” of information that was available to Darwin at the time. There was absolutely no framework for any kind of causal explanation: the field of genetics was not developed until the mid-19th century and molecular biology was not understood until the 1930s and 40s. Without a genetic framework, Darwin had no means to explain how traits were passed from one generation to the next which clearly inhibits his ability to provide any comprehensive causal explanation. Any explanation would also have to leave out molecular biology, giving Darwin an extremely small set of possible causal explanations to work off of. Darwin’s hypothetical causal explanation would also not be based on observed phenomena: the observed phenomena at the time was biodiversity, variation, and adaptation. These were explained by his heritability and natural selection. If he were to provide a further explanation, like a mechanism for inheritance, this would not be in terms of phenomena observed and empirical evidence because a framework required to observe the molecular processes underlying genetics did not exist. Clearly, Darwin could not provide a pragmatically testable causal explanation, and thus, any explanation would have been unscientific.</p> <p>A possible counterexample is that Darwin and Newton could have provided some sort of causal explanation that was testable. For example, Darwin could have said that there were particles that transmitted traits from parent to offspring, and it could have been testable by looking at the development of a fetus through a microscope. While this is conceivable, it still would likely not have been possible to observe these phenomena when we look at the constraints of the time: lack available technology, the absence of the necessary scientific knowledge, and the prevailing paradigm of a fixity of species and special creation.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="nature-of-scientific-revolution"/><category term="philosophy,"/><category term="science,"/><category term="nature,"/><category term="lamarck,"/><category term="darwin"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Does a Leibniz-style critique of Darwinian evolution hold any weight?]]></summary></entry></feed>